Herald: Hi, Welcome to this apparently very popular talk
because there are still like around 20 people besides this door
so there is obviously big interest in this topic
lets welcome our speakers from Positive Technologies:
Sergey Gordeychik and Gleb Gritsai.
Applause.
Speakers: Thanks everybody who has arrived.
First of all I want to say that SCADA Strangelove is a collective approach, its collective product
and we're just frontmen. With our team, I think this [...] a lot of applause.
This guys work at
So, why are here?
Because according to our information, our analysis, Europe, worst protected region in the world
if we look from SCADA security perspective.
Most of SCADA systems exposed to Internet have well known vulnerabilities
like default passwords, default configuration, and error(?).
Italy [is] first in this list. Why? I don't know
Maybe because it is Italy
Special Thanks to Siemens ProductCERT. I don't know whether there are guys from Siemens here.
Thanks again because they're really professionals and I was really surprised because,
they not only provide [...] quick response to email but even provide patches.
It's something unusal in ICS industy.
I will talk a lot about Siemens. Why? Because Siemens is elephant
Siemens is everywhere. It's most common target during our penetration test.
during search in Internet