The name of my talk is
"Just because you are paranoid doesn't mean your phone isn't listening to everyword you say"
And I want to show you guys my greates technologic archivement in the entire presentation
I created a 1.9GB powerpoint presentation
and audience starts laughing
applaus
So
if this thing finishes and we can
power threw the powerpoint without my laptop bursting into flame
I thing we have really acomplished something
and as last time I come bearing gifts
We gona donate all of the hardware we pressend to the horror hacking area outside
so after this presentation, if you want to play with
the CISCO phone we are talking about
you can absolutely do that
The hardware is yours!
And we also are giving away one SuperSnazzy
partially assembled
ThingPowner-Kit
to somebody in the audience
who answers a question during the presentation
and we will talk about what this thingreally does.
in a little bit
but a little bit about who I am
and what I do
I am now a 5th year Phd candidate
at Colombia University Intrusion Detektions Lab
and here are some of my puplications
that I have put out in the last five years.
What I do, I spend the last 5 yeas thinking about ways to defent embedded systems
agaisnt exploaitation.
And threw out that time, you know, sometimes I talk to a person and they really get what I am saying,
they understands why we need to secrue this things
but other times, you know, the folks I talk to have this glaze overlook
yeah, I know they are thinking: "This guy is a conspiricy nut. What do you mean?
Somebody can hack my printer and lsiten to me threw it or what?"
So the last few years I spend some time comming up with examples of
exploitations agaisnt embbedded systems you find everywhere
that have real world consequences
So for example, I came here last year and they presented the APR vulnerability
, the firmware modification vulnerability which essentialy allows you to change the firmware on HP printers without you
doing any much besides printing to the device.
The attac itself was fairly simpel to make, all it took was a lot of monkey
soldering, some reverse engeineereing and a arduino and soem duck tape
but, you know I thing we had, well, impact because this year HP released firmware updates to more then 60 models of there firmware
to their printers all fixing this vulnerability so because of the presentation and because of a comunnity
like this one, that cares about embbeded sesurity we made some actual positive influence in the world.
That thing is a good thing.
applaus year! Thank you!
And we reasons why I care about embedded security is, you know, this:
In the olden days, you had your big bad internet but you were okay because you had this thign called the firewall
which protected your server against hax0r kitten on the internet, right?
And hax0r kitten sucks because, you know, once they take all your marbles and break into your server
and the longest time the name of the game was to get threw or around the firewall
so you could get access to the server and compromise it and have it do some intreseting thing
And maybe even extract some information
And thats what the netwrok looked like but if you paid attention to what is
really on this network, it's not just the server or this firewall.
You have this thigns that look like computers but, you know, we call them printers, right, and phones
So in 2000 now, if I were to go after this network I would directly go to the printer
For example use APR vulnerability that I talked about last year
Send a very nice resume which would change the firmware on the printer
And once I get controll of this device, I could, you know, steal all your super secret sensitivy information
your print out of the thing but really, that is not my end goal.
My goal is to use this as a launching of point so I can compromise other computers on your network
like this phone and once I have access to all of this embedded systems
I can the nsue these guys to then attac the general purpose computer on your network
And now if you come along and you notice that I owned your server
you probably wipe the server and, you know, I come back the next day and own you threw the phone again, as an example.
And I can also use this devices to extract sensitive information out of the network
So, I saw this in an newspaper article, this is an wired article that I saw, I think in february or march
and the story was that some guy broke into this waterpump station in texas
It turned out to be not the case but you know, this guy is really serious about pointing at his computer saying
"I am gona look this system down! No hacker is gona get inside here!"
But when I saw this article I realized that he is not even looking into the direction he should be
because behind his arm is the device I would go after if I was able to get into this network
I thought it was a cisco phone but I got this very nice email yesterday saying:
"Based on the carvature of the device, it probabably is an avire(??)
I do not know.
You know, this peaked my intrest and I started looking into at places where CISCO phones are being used
turns out, they are used everywhere
Right? So this is Dwight(?) from the office
this is the very typical corporate phone
ahm, I guess we are in Germany so this is Dwichts analog laughter from Germany
I find these phones all about the place in hospitals
Here is a picture of Obama in the oval office, on his desk is a CISCO phone
and next to him is Byden(?), he gets nothing because he is Byden(?)
And here is Obama again with a CISCO phone, you can't really see but you notice the windows are a bit cureved in this picture
and this is bcause this is a CISCO phone on Airforce One, right, this is Obamas presedential plane.
So these things are all over the place
And I showed this picture off at a DARPA meeting a few weeks ago and I guess it was not so funny to them but I think it is really funny
This is the Ex-director of the CIA, right? And next to him, right? And he is very happy
because behind him you see three CISCO phones. And he is really happy because he knows something what I do not know.
He knows these phones are really secure. So I look at the vendor documentation.
There is a really thick book about why this phone and the voip enterprise solution is very secure.
It has 202 pages to convice you of that.
It says:
Everything is signed firmware, so you get a check for that
Everything has FIPS certified crypto on this phone, whatever that means, so thats another check.
There is a secure operating system, undisclosed, propreatary but it is good so thats okay
There is Java audience starts laughing
Well, this was written 2002 so you know, having Java in the thing made it secure and it was great.
And you know there is a minimal attac survace and the hole thing has a secure admin interface meaning https and ssh which we will talk about.
But if you get past all the vendors speak, this is what you are looking at. Okay, at the hardware of the hole thing.
Here is not really a phone but a general purpose computer put into this plastic case that makes it look like a telephone.
At the heart of this computer you have two chips, on the left you have dispension(?) flash chip
, on the right you have the system on the chip, a SoC, rebranded by CISCO but it really is a Broadcom BCM1100 VoIP Engine
This was really the only image I was able to find about this chip open on the internet.
But if you break it down, this is what you have.
You have a SoC and next to the Soc you have flash, you know, they call it ROM but it is really not ROM.
You have soem RAM
and you stick a ethernet phy on it
and you get a computer and if you change the SoC, change it to a Marvell, this will give you the HP printer I talekd about last year
But what makes this thing a phone is the fact that there is a hardwire microphone attached to it
and there is this little switch that is here that tells than the hand held is picked up, it is called the OFFHook switch.
This is what the hardware look like, lets look what the software actually does.
it does sign everything so then the phones boots up it verifies the sigature on the loads it runs. So whats true.
On top of that it also checksums every file, you know, it does both things.
And like the name suggests, it is a unix like environment so the thing we are working with is called CNU hwich stands for
CISCO Native Uninx
and unlike the printer I talked about last year this thing has processes so we are really moving up in the world
It has memory isolation so different procecies have different memory spaces, right, so they are not falling over each other, hwich is good.
And you have non writable text sections and non executable data sections.
And on top of that this phone does really has a very minimal attac surfrace so all the features it runs are basically turned off at boot time
Although you can enable these features over TFTP which we will talk in a little bit.
And the system is locked down! So the only thingthat runs as root on this phone is the init process which means
if you find a vulnerability somewhere in a non priviledged process you will havea hard time getting root on this phone.
And on top of that it has SSH, HTTPS and all this good stuff.
And I like to point out if you want to play with the firmware images and the binaries that I am taling about
you can actaully go to this webside and download an unpacker that unpacks all this stuff that has been around for, I thing, 2009
I think the hosting company here is very teriible because half the timethe side is down but the link isn't broken so keep trying.
So lets talk about some of these security features and what it really means, okay?
It has 100% signed firmware, which is good but this thing is really only applied at boot time
which means after the phone boots up, you can login and download any binary you want
and download it to the tmp-directory over tftp and execute it
So you still get arbitrary execution on the phone.
Just not while it is booting up.
So that is not very useful
and then on top of the signature verification, all the important files are checksumed
but /etc/passwd is one of these files and if you have noptice, /etc/passwd contains the default
user, right, the password is "user", really big secret
that is guanrteed to be on every cisco phone ever made. If you want to disable this acount you actually cannot do it
because the phone would notice that you modified a file that is not supossed to be modified and it will restore the default user and password on the phone.
So cannot get rid of this, this is guranteed to be on every single cisco phone that you come accross
Can't change it!
And if you change it you have broken signature verification, right, that is voiding your warranty.
And then there is ssh. There is so much lolz in ssh that we are going to save it for a hole different independetn section of the presentation
But we will get back to it.
Just wanna say ssh here, the way it is implemented makes it actually worse then having telnet.
laughter
We will talk about that.
Okay, I am gona hand it over to Mike who is gona talk about our initial attemps
to break into this badboy.
So lets start talking about exploitation of the phone.