Opening Event - bios
Good morning, Hamburg, not Berlin
This is not the keynote, so if you need anything important to do,
get it done, the keynote will
start in a few minutes
and by the way, I am not Jacob, I am bios, hello!
one slight technical problem...
okay, the first slide doesn't show (yet)
No, no, it's not powerpoint,
it's free, it's better,  it's libreoffice.
This is not the keynote, we already covered this, so...
Big important changes: It's crazy how many of you are here at this early hour in the morning, it is basically still at night
and cool to see that you all managed to the right location
we mentioned this, I think the stream is already up,
so if anyone is in Berlin and sees the stream, I don't know
if the bcc shows the stream;
there is still some time to get here
the train takes about two hours;
I had that problem yesterday
And welcome everyone! Great to see you!
I you have a talk
one warning to the fellow speakers:
if you have a talk tomorrow
or a talk where some time is available
to get up to the stage here,
this room is amazing and a bit scary
People all around me!
Okay, let's get started!
Some new things we have this year here:
we have the hackcenter as every year,
But we also have assemblies.
Hopefully, Most of you already
saw this in the wiki and on the blog, because now it is too late to start an assembly
because all the space is distributed to the assemblies.
and When you walk around the building you will see some signs
announcing the assembly which has been placed there
there are also some "shared" tables. The Meaning
is a bit of the shared situation; first I thought I can just go there and grab a seat,
but shared spaces are meant for the assemblies,
so if they hold a talk or hold a workshop, they can use the shared space
so if you squat there, they will probably ask very politely to move away.
But you have to give up the seat there.
In the wiki you can also see which assemblies have workshops
and many assemblies also will give talks,
so probably there will be a timetable in the wiki
where you can see where which shared space will be used.
for some assembly business.
What else? we had a presale this year again, unfortunately, we
couldn't implement the much asked feature of "Bad Gateway",
a very famous german holiday place,
but we managed to sell many tickets,
we will give some statistics at the closing event.
There are still some tickets on sale, so
if you see the stream, you can come and get a tcket.
I think we have about 1000 tickets per day,
so there should be a ticket for everyone.
Yeah, Also in the presale ticket system, hopefully
everyone who wanted some clothes already ordered it., because
I am not sure how many tshirts we will have left after the congress,
but if you ordered, please collect it today.
If you can't, come to the congress today, write us an email or
annonce it, otherweise we will distribute the not-fetched t-shirts tomorrow.
It is really important, so do it today.
We have a "Fahrplan"
since yesterday evening; we have version 1.0
but  I think it is already outdated.
And we have these paper plans, they are really great including a map of the building
the version on the paper is already outdated.
I think one room appeared out of nowhere and is now on the Fahrplan.
So, check the online version and twitter will announce updates.
Yeah, Volunteers: really, really important.
If you walk around the building and interact with the people here,
nearly everyone but I think if you walk around in the public areas, you interact with is volunteering, so be nice.
If you are at the bar and they run temporary out of mate, be nice,
wait a minute and evenb better, go ask if you can help them.
we have an angel meeting, I believe one is right now,
but the next will be in the evening, so ask there what you can help, just go there, and ask what you can do.
we also have an online version, the "Engelsystem",
you can also register there and sign some shifts, so eg the Video-Angels around here are volunteers.
All the poeple behind the nice blinking lights are volunteers
okay, and one update to the talks: There will be translations!
Last Minute information here, Hi,
So we are trying to setting up a live translator team,
we've got around ten people right now,
everybody fluent in english and understanding german
quite enough is welcome to join us,
we are meeting   at 11:30 out here, follow the blog, there is a post as well,
we need people to help us with live translations, and we are trying to do
all 27 german talks into english, and there will be live stream for that, and there will be recordings,
so if you don't understand enough german, all german talks will at least be attempted to be translated in english.
there might be also a DECT Channel for the translation, I am not entirely sure about that, please check the wiki.
Thanks!
Okay, hopefully, nothing urgent or extreme will happen, but if you are in some kind of emergency,
I don't know, you cut yourself, you touch the wrong end of the soldering item,
we have a medical team standing by, they are next to the cash desk,
you can call them, you can call 112 or 911, but please make sure you are on DECT.
Don't call them on GSM if you are bored and need someone to hang out.
Apparently that has happened before.
New this year, we had it last year, but I don't think it wasn't so organized as this year;
we have a network abuse team, so if you you are on the stream
and happen to be a network provider and something strange is happening on your network
and you suspect we're to blame,
I think the full page for abuse handeling is also online or check the RIPE-Entry.
You probably know what to do.
Yeah but we also have some abuse and ani-harrassment team, they're available at 113
and they also provide deescalation services, so if you have some problems
or if somethings strange is happening, just give them a call
and they will talk to you and will try to help you.
okay, so, we are nearly at the end.
More information: you probably know it, we have a wiki which is really extensive and updated all the time,
so check it, there will be much to discover.
we have the infodesk again, they are also down at the entrance.
really, get a map, I got lost already I think three times yesterday, trying to find some area, and it was like
"it used to be there, but I was on the wrong floor, and there are sub-floors" and
the maps are great! Wander around, Discover all the stuff,
There is much to see, this building is really, really huge
Also, have fun and keep on hacking, be excellent to each other, and thanks for listening.
So, we are making about five minutes of minutes of break
to set up everything and then you'll see the next speaker, the keynote